<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Artillery-Company of London at St. Mary-le-Bow, December 2, 1684, and now published at their desire by Benjamin Calamy ...</title>
            <author>Calamy, Benjamin, 1642-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31853</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C220</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5768</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13689645</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13689645</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101390</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31853)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101390)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 840:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Artillery-Company of London at St. Mary-le-Bow, December 2, 1684, and now published at their desire by Benjamin Calamy ...</title>
                  <author>Calamy, Benjamin, 1642-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Baker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XXVI, 52 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101390:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the <hi>Artillery-Company</hi> OF LONDON, AT S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Mary-le-Bow, <hi>DECEMBER</hi> 2, 1684. And now Publiſhed at their deſire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> BENJAMIN CALAMY, <hi>D. D. One of his Majeſties Chaplains in Ordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Baker,</hi> Printer to the Honourable Society, at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls Church-yard,</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101390:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101390:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Sir <hi>William Prichard</hi> Knight and Alderman, Preſident of the <hi>Artillery-Company.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">To the Right Honourable Sir <hi>James Smith,</hi> LORD MAYOR, VICE-PRESIDENT.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the Right Worſhipful Sir <hi>Matthew Andrews</hi> TREASURER.</head>
            <head type="sub">As alſo to the Right Honourable
<list>
                  <item>Earl of <hi>Aran,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Earl of <hi>Huntingdon,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Earl of <hi>Salisbury,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Cholmondeley.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">To the Right Worſhipful
<list>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Richard Temple,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Peter Daniel,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Samuel Daſhwood,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captain <hi>William Davies,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">STEWARDS. And to the whole Court of Aſſiſtants, Field-Officers, Captains, and Gentlemen, Profeſſing and Exerciſing. Arms in that Renowned and Honourable Society.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SO many excellent Books have been of late Written in defence of Loyalty and the Government, in anſwer to thoſe virulent and Seditious Pamphlets and Libels that have been Publiſhed amongſt us, that we might reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably hope there ſhould be hardly now left one diſaffected Man
<pb facs="tcp:101390:3"/>in the Nation: Yet it appears by thoſe diſcontents that are ſtill whiſper'd, that there is great need of an anniverſary meeting of this Illuſtrious Society, which not only by their Example doth encourage others to be Loyal, but can alſo force thoſe to be ſuch, who perhaps might have but little mind to it otherwiſe. And notwithſtanding all that hath been ſaid or Printed for obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Lawful Authority, there are many ſo ſlenderly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and ſo ready on all occaſions to Relapſe, that there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be frequent uſe of ſome plain Diſcourſes, to ſhew the wickedneſs, as well as miſchievouſneſs of all diſloyal Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. To do this in ſome meaſure, is the honeſt deſign of the following Sermon, which is now humbly preſented to your favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable acceptance, By</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> &amp;c.</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant,</hi> Benjamin Calamy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101390:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the <hi>Artillery-Company.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>St. MATTHEW XXVI. 52.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Then ſaid Jeſus unto him, put up again thy Sword into his place: for all they that take the Sword ſhall periſh with the Sword.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Can eaſily imagine ſome amongſt you upon the firſt hearing of theſe words ready to tell me, that this advice of our Lords is by no means ſuited or proper to this illuſtrious Aſſembly, conſiſting of Men ſo long Trained up, and ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently skill'd in Martial exerciſes. To bid thoſe, who ſo well know the uſe of the Sword, to <hi>put it into its place,</hi> and ſuffer it to ruſt in its Scabbard, ſounds like a diſmiſſion or disbanding of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned and honourable Society, and an hard cenſure of your noble Profeſſion, as unlawful or Antichriſtian, and infinitely dangerous too, if <hi>all they that take the Sword ſhall periſh by the Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:101390:4"/>
            <p> But if we better conſider what our Saviour here ſaith, we ſhall not find any thing in this Text againſt the uſe of the Sword upon a juſt and neceſſary oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, or when it is duely put into our hands by thoſe, who have from God the power of the Sword com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them. For he did not command his Diſciples to fling it away, as of no further uſe under the Goſpel; as if no other Sword was now ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary but that of the Spirit; or as if all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were bound tamely to yield up themſelves an eaſy prey to violent and injurious Men, and in no caſe to repel unjuſt force by force. No: our bleſſed Lord but a little before, <hi>viz.</hi> the very ſame Night in which he ſpake the words of my Text, had adviſed his Diſciples, thoſe of them who had no Swords, <hi>to ſell their Garments and buy one;</hi> thereby allowing them to provide Arms ſufficient for their defence againſt lawleſs Robbers and Cut-throats, who were very common and numerous in thoſe Countries, through which they were to paſs for the propagation of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour did never intend to ty all his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hands, and expoſe them naked to be Invaded and Aſſaulted by any one that had a mind to it. To oppoſe force againſt unjuſt force is allow'd to every Man by the Law of Nature, which natural right our Religion hath not cancel'd nor reſtrained, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided always that we thus draw our Swords only againſt private Perſons, and not againſt thoſe who
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101390:4"/>have Warrant or Command of publick Authority to vouch their force againſt us; and that it be in ſuch caſes of extremity, where we cannot defend our ſelves by the regular courſe of calling in the Aſſiſtance of the Law or Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>Nay further, in the very words of my Text our Saviour doth expreſly allow the uſe of the Sword in the hands of the Supreme power, or by Comiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Authority from it. For when he ſaith <hi>they ſhall periſh by the Sword,</hi> he means by the Sword of the Magiſtrate, which ſhall juſtly cut off ſuch Offenders.</p>
            <p>Thus from the words themſelves we have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient evidence, that our Saviour did not forbid the uſe of the Sword; either in our own neceſſary defence, or at the Command and direction of the Supreme Governours: In which two caſes only it was ever lawful for private Perſons. And in this matter the Laws of our Religion have made no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration. We may ſtill defend our ſelves by the Sword from the unjuſt Aſſaults of private Perſons, when we have no other Remedy; and the Soveraigns of every Nation and Kingdom have the ſame power over their Subjects perſons, fortunes and lives, that they had before Chriſtianity appeared in the World, that they had from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ſince Men firſt entered into Societies, and lived under Government.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour therefore in my Text forbids the uſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101390:5"/>of the Sword only on that particular occaſion, or the like, on which it was drawn by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> which was this;</p>
            <p>A great company of Souldiers, and other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers from the chief Prieſts and Phariſees, with the Traitour <hi>Judas</hi> to conduct them, were ſent to Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend our Bleſſed Saviour in the Garden, whither he had retired. This the Diſciples thought a fit oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to ſhew their courage and conſtancy to their Lord and Maſter, by venturing their own Lives to reſcue him from the mercyleſs hands of his bloody enemies. They asked him therefore, <hi>Lord ſhall we ſmite with the Sword?</hi> and St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who was natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of a more hot temper and bolder ſpirit than the reſt of the Apoſtles, without tarrying for an Anſwer drew his Sword, and ſtruck at the chiefeſt and moſt buſy of them, (ſome gueſs him to be the Man that Commanded the Party, and had the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to ſeize our Lord) and he out off his ear. But our Saviour liked not this raſh and ungovernable zeal, and therefore intreated thoſe who had him in their power to ſuffer him but ſo long, till by a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous touch he healed the Wound, and turning to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> bad him <hi>put up his Sword again into his place.</hi> For at preſent there was not the leaſt juſt occaſion for it, (as great an one as he might think was now offered to him) that his Cauſe ſtood not in need of any ſuch irregular defence. It was not for lack of help, that he thus quietly ſubmitted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101390:5"/>but out of reſpect to that Authority, which imploy'd theſe Souldiers and Officers. Had he any deſire to be forceably delivered out of their hands, did he want any to fight for him, he could eaſily ſpeak to his Father, and he would preſently ſend more than Twelve Legions of Angels to appear for his reſcue. <hi>For he that taketh the Sword,</hi> that is at his own pleaſure or for his own humour without ſufficient order or Authority, when it is not put into his hands, but he <hi>taketh</hi> it without warrantable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, or uſeth it againſt a Lawful Authority, <hi>ſhall periſh by the Sword,</hi> ſhall and ought to ſuffer for ſo doing, is guilty of a capital crime, for which he forfeits his Life to Juſtice here, and of a moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſin, for which without Repentance he ſhall ſtand condemned hereafter. <hi>Put up again thy Sword into his place, for all they that take the Sword ſhall periſh with the Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Saviour here plainly condemns all reſiſtance of Lawful Authority by force and violence, ſince he would not ſuffer the Sword to be drawn againſt thoſe, who acted by a juſt Authority, though what they did was barbarouſly unjuſt. Whether it be in any caſe lawful by force and violence to reſiſt Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is truly ſtiled <hi>the greateſt caſe of Conſcience in the world,</hi> ſince ſo very much doth depend upon the right reſolution of it. And if it could be plainly made out that our Saviour, or his Apoſtles, did give Subjects right or liberty on any pretence to take
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101390:6"/>up Arms, or to fight againſt the Lawful powers, I ſhould look upon it as the greateſt objection that could be brought againſt Chriſtianity. For it would be an eternal ſcandal, and indelible reproach againſt our Religion, if it countenanced any thing, that was ſo manifeſtly inconſiſtent with the peace of Societies and civil Government.</p>
            <p>There is nothing more evident than that this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, that it is Lawful in ſome caſes for Subjects by force to reſiſt their King and Sovereign, doth open a wide door to all manner of diſorder and confuſion. For if it ever be Lawful for Subjects to reſiſt the Soveraign power, then it follows that the Subjects have always a right to judge, whether their preſent caſe be ſuch, as that they may Lawfully reſiſt in, and if they be Judges, this Propoſition that ſubjects may reſiſt in ſome caſes, of which themſelves are Judges, is the ſame, as to ſay, that they may do it whenever they ſhall think fit for to do it; and thus any ſuſpicion or diſcontent taken up againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, any grievance we can fancy, any thing our Governour doth that is miſconſtrued or miſinter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted, will be thought a juſtifiable pretence for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up Arms againſt him, which neceſſarily lays the Foundation of everlaſting Wars and troubles.</p>
            <p>I might therefore ſufficiently evince the falſeneſs of this Principle from the inevitable miſchievous conſequences of it; but it rather becomes the place I now ſtand in to ſhew how wicked and unchriſtian
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101390:6"/>a Doctrine it is. And there is nothing more plainly and ſolemnly condemned by the Laws of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than for Subjects by force of Arms on any occaſion to reſiſt the Supreme Power and Authority, let it be in one ſingle perſon, or more, according to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent forms of Government in ſeveral Countries: Or to ſpeak as the caſe is amongſt our ſelves, it is never Lawful by our Religion on any pretence to reſiſt the King, or any Authoriſed by the King, whom we all acknowledge in the Oath of <hi>Supremacy</hi> to be <hi>the only Supreme Governour of this Realm,</hi> and if he be the only <hi>Supreme,</hi> there is no power on Earth equal or co-ordinate to his any more, than there is any Superiour.</p>
            <p>Had we no other proof of this, as we have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, but theſe words of our Saviour to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> we might from them ſufficiently learn his Mind and Will concerning reſiſtance of the Supreme Power. Where I ſhall obſerve firſt, what a fair pretence and Plea St. <hi>Peter</hi> and the Diſciples had for drawing the Sword or taking up Arms, and then I ſhall explain the grounds or reaſons upon which our Saviour for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad them, and ſo ſharply rebuked St. <hi>Peter;</hi> laſtly I ſhall draw one or two inferences from the whole.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider what plauſible pretence St. <hi>Peter</hi> and the Diſciples here had for the drawing of the Sword; and ſurely if ever there was or can be any caſe, wherein reſiſtance of Lawful Authority by force is juſtifiable, it muſt had been ſo in this we are now diſcourſing of. For</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101390:7"/> 1. This act of St. <hi>Peter</hi> was purely defenſive. Here was no Plot or deſign laid againſt the <hi>Chief Prieſts</hi> or <hi>Elders</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> much leſs againſt the Life or Dignity of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or the Authority of his Deputy in <hi>Judaea.</hi> No Combination nor <hi>Aſſociation</hi> for the defence of our Saviour, no holy League or Covenant taken, nor engagement entred into to root out the Highprieſthood and Jewiſh Hierarchy, and to ſtand by one another with their Lives and Fortunes; no naming of a General, or liſting of Souldiers in the Cauſe; no contribution of Plate or Money for the carrying it on; no contrivance of any Inſurrection or ſeizing the Guards, or ſtirring up the people againſt the Government; no ſecret con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults about the management of the buſineſs; but only an haſty and raſh attempt to ſecure our Saviours Perſon from the violence offered to him; which if they had by force effected, and actually delivered him out of the hands of the Officers that came to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him, there in all probability the Tumult would have ſtopped, and no further damage or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice happened to the publick State. So that here was not any dangerous Conſpiracy againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, nor a direct taking up Arms againſt it, but their greateſt fault ſeems to be only a diſorderly zeal for the Life and ſafety of their Lord and Maſter, to preſerve which they thought themſelves in gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and honour bound.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The violence here offered to our Saviour by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101390:7"/>Chief Prieſts and Officers was as baſe and vile piece of injuſtice, as ever was acted by Men: Moſt foul treachery in <hi>Judas,</hi> invincible malice in the <hi>Chief Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Elders</hi> againſt the moſt innocent perſon that ever lived in the World. I may well call their ſpite againſt him invincible, ſince thoſe marvellous good works he had done amongſt them, all the kindneſſes they had received from him, the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable ſweetneſs and obligingneſs of his temper and deportment could not ſubdue it.</p>
            <p>Now this St. <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of our Saviours intimate friends and followers could not be ignorant of. They knew how the Rulers of the <hi>Jews</hi> had all along laid their traps to enſnare him, invented their <hi>Sham-plots</hi> to find matter of accuſation againſt him, with what unwearied diligence they had Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted him, and all that adhered to him, and were now at laſt reſolved on his Death. And who could be ſafe in their Lives and Eſtates, if ſuch exemplary vertue and innocence could not protect our Bleſſed Saviour? So that here their civil Liberties and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties were highly concerned. If our Governours prevail, and by ſuch manifeſt injuſtice take away this Mans Life, the Lord knows who of us by ſuch wicked Arts and ſubornation of witneſſes and methods of violence ſhall go next. This is ſuch an inſtance of Arbitrarineſs and Tyranny, as is not to be endured by a free people.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is further to be conſidered that not only
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101390:8"/>their civil Liberties and Birthright, but the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was alſo in great danger. This perſon in whoſe defence St. <hi>Peter</hi> drew his Sword was no other than the Son of God, the Saviour of the World, that great Prophet of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake of old time, and whom their whole Nation had ſo long expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: That Divine Preacher of Righteouſneſs, whom God had ſent into the World theſe laſt days to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct mankind, and diſcover his whole will to us, and by it to conduct us to eternal Life. Now this feizing of his Perſon was a downright rejecting the true <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> a deſign to root out his holy Doctrine, which his enemies doubted not but would dy with him. Who would not ſtretch a little and venture ſomething in ſo Sacred and ſo Glorious a Cauſe? Did it become the Diſciples to ſtand upon little ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceties and punctilio's of duty, when they were haling away the Son of God himſelf, as the vileſt Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, and all that was dear to them lay at ſtake? or needed they to fear Gods diſpleaſure, for reſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one ſo dear to him out of the hands of thoſe wretched Miſcreants, who would treat him with all imaginable ſpite and cruelty? Thus you ſee it was their Love only and concern for the beſt perſon, the beſt Religion, that inſpirited St. <hi>Peter</hi> and the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with courage and reſolution to attack the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and Officers that came againſt their Maſter.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The force that was oppoſed, or the reſſiſtance that was made was only againſt the inferiour and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101390:8"/>meaneſt Officers and Servants. The Sword was drawn neither againſt <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelf, nor any ſent by him as <hi>Herod</hi> or <hi>Pilate,</hi> nor yet againſt any of the <hi>Chief Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Elders</hi> of the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, but only againſt ſome of their ordinary <hi>Malignant</hi> Servants and Officers; and that too at a time when but very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle power remained to the <hi>Jews,</hi> who could not judge in <hi>Capital</hi> Cauſes, nor put any to Death by their own Authority. St. <hi>Peter</hi> might have pleaded, that he deſign'd no hurt or miſchief to the perſons of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, whom he acknowledged to be Sacred and Inviolable; that he owned the Authority of the <hi>Chief Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Elders,</hi> did not fight againſt them, but for them againſt their unjuſt <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who came treacherouſly in the Night to ſurprize our Saviour, that they might deliver him up to <hi>Pilate</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Preſident; and this without any Commiſſion from him, who had the chief Juridiction in <hi>Jewry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, St. <hi>Peter</hi> only reſiſted unjuſt and illegal Violence: He thought himſelf under the ſtrongeſt Obligations of Love and Gratitude to his Lord and Maſter to do it. It was zeal for <hi>Chriſt</hi> inflamed him, he could not endure to ſee the Son of God ſo baſely uſed. Yet notwithanding all theſe Circumſtances, which I have alledged in his favour, he was ſeverely reprehended by our Saviour for drawing his Sword, the fact was condemned, and thoſe who ſhould here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after imitate him by taking the Sword in like caſes Sentenced as worthy of Death.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101390:9"/> 2. I proceed to enquire into the grounds and reaſons, upon which our Saviour blamed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned this Fact of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and we ſhall find theſe two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe he had no competent Authority to draw his Sword.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe fighting in defence of our Saviour and his Religion was utterly inconſiſtent with his deſign, and the Nature of his Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe he had no competent Authority to juſtifie his drawing his Sword. So ſaith our Saviour, <hi>All they that take the Sword,</hi> of their own heads, who without leave or Commiſſion uſurp the right of the Magiſtrate, ſhall ſuffer the puniſhment due by Law to <hi>Murderers, who ſo ſheddeth Mans Blood, by Man ſhall his Blood be ſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God Almighty is the ſole Lord and Maſter of Life and Death. No Man hath of himſelf power over his own Life, much leſs over anothers, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently cannot transfer any ſuch power. What is therefore called <hi>jus gladii</hi> or the power of the Sword muſt be put into the hands of the Soveraign by God alone, whoſe Miniſter he is, and not by the people, who cannot give what they never had. Who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Fights with the allowance, or at the Command of the Supreme power, fights by Gods Authority too; by whoſe leave and appointment he takes away the Lives of the Kings enemies. And to pretend to fight for God without any Authority from the King,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101390:9"/>muſt either ſuppoſe a private direction, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from God, (which is all impoſture) or it makes every private perſon a Soveraign, which is indeed to deſtroy the Nature both of Soveraign and Subject.</p>
            <p>Our Bleſſed Saviour here pronounceth him worthy of Death, who ſhould draw his Sword either againſt or without a Lawful Authority, though it be to ſecure the greateſt innocence from the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and illegal Perſecution: And can we then poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſire a plainer, or more expreſs Text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture againſt all reſiſtance of Lawful Authority by force and violence, than theſe words of our Lord. For if (excepting the caſe of private defence, in which the conſent of the Supreme Power is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) we are never to uſe the Sword, but when we receive Authority to do it from the Publick Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, then to be ſure it is never Lawful to uſe it againſt him; unleſs we will imagine the King to Authorize Men, and give them Commiſſion to fight againſt himſelf, as thoſe in our late Rebellion did, who pretended to fight againſt his Perſon by his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, a conceit as abſurd, as Traiterous.</p>
            <p>Now by this one precept of non-Reſiſtance to the higher Powers our Saviour hath beſt ſecured the Rights of Princes, the liberty of the Subject and the Peace of Societies.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By this our Saviour hath ſecured the Rights of Soveraign Princes. This being an eſſential part of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101390:10"/>the Soveraign power to be unaccountable and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtable. For that power which is to give account unto, or may be reſiſted by any other power on Earth, is not the Soveraign power of a Nation, but it is ſubject to thoſe who cannot controul it. Thus if it were Lawful for the Body of the people in general or their repreſentatives in any caſe to take up Arms, and reſiſt, then is the King Soveraign only during pleaſure, and the people ſubject no longer, than they ſhall think fit: And it is truly ſaid, that <hi>He hath only an empty ſhadow of Power and Authority,</hi> who is cloathed with the <hi>Robes of Majeſty,</hi> and is entruſted with the <hi>Scepter,</hi> whilſt the power of the Sword is in another hand. If by our Religion it had been on any pretence permitted to have reſiſted, our Saviour had utterly deſtroyed all the rights of Government, Kings would have had a very uncertain precarious Title to their Crowns, he had made their Subjects Judges of their Soveraigns actions, and conſequently ſuperiour to them; in a word, he had dethroned all Monarchs by transferring that abſolute uncontrolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Power, which in all Governments muſt be lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſomewhere, from the King to the people.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By forbidding reſiſtance our Saviour hath moſt effectually ſecured the Rights, Liberties and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſubject, which certainly are beſt preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved under Government. For the greateſt danger ſubjects are in is not from their Prince, but from their fellow ſubjects; and for this purpoſe God hath
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101390:10"/>inſtituted Government to ſecure us from the violence of other injurious perſons, without which we ſhould live as amongſt <hi>Bears</hi> and <hi>Tygers,</hi> nay <hi>without it neither Houſe, nor City, nor Nation, nor Mankind, nor Nature, nor the World it ſelf can ſubſiſt,</hi> as <hi>Tully</hi> ſpeaks in his Third Book of <hi>Laws.</hi> When the Hedge and Wall is once broken down, and the fence taken away, we ſtrait become liable to the incurſions of all the Rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Beaſts of prey, and to avoid Tyranny or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of our Governours, we ſoon are made ſlaves to the meaneſt of the people, as it uſually happens in Civil Wars, and proſperous Rebellions. This Doctrine therefore is ſo far from enſlaving the people, or deſtroying their Natural right of ſelf-preſervation, that it indeed teacheth us the beſt way to defend our ſelves, and ſecure our Liberties.</p>
            <p>Publick Government is always the beſt means of ſelf-defence; and therefore to reſiſt, or to endeavour to overthrow the Government at any time, is to take away and deſtroy the beſt means we have of defending our own Lives, Properties, and Rights. It may indeed, as the caſe may ſome times happen, free us from one Tyrant, but then it oppoſes us to the rage and luſt of Ten Thouſand. Our Rights and Liberties are not any ways more certainly violated, than by civil commotions and inteſtine Tumults, and broils: and oppreſſion, under the worſt Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is not ſo great an evil, as the devaſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and deſolations that are made by ſubjects re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101390:11"/>and rebelling againſt their Soveraign. On which account it is reported of the old <hi>Perſians,</hi> that upon the Death of any of their Kings the people were allowed ſome few days freedom from all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that <hi>by the miſchiefs, ſlaughters, outrages and rapines, committed in that ſhort interval, they might be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of the neceſſity and uſefulneſs of Government,</hi> and that the worſt was vaſtly better than none at all.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, By this precept of non-reſiſtance our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour hath provided for the peace of Societies, which can never be maintained, where this principle is once admitted, that it is lawful in ſome caſes to reſiſt the Supreme Authority. For the beſt Governours, the moſt equal and juſt Governments are diſpleaſing to ſome or other. It is impoſſible that things ſhould be always adminiſtred with that exact fairneſs, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, and ſucceſs too, as not to offend ſome, who ſhall think themſelves oppreſs'd and wrong'd; and if they think ſo, this ſhall be ground enough to diſturb the peace of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Hence there muſt be eternal jealouſies between the Prince and people; watching for all advantages one againſt the other; continual undermining and weakning one anothers intereſt and force; and nothing could be the reſult of ſuch a conſtitution, but endleſs tumult and confuſion. So that it is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feating the very end of all ſocieties; and liberty of defence, if allowed to private perſons againſt their ſuperiours, would make the condition of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101390:11"/>far worſe, than it can well be under the moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and illimited Monarchy.</p>
            <p>I know here very Tragical Stories are told, and ſtrange conſequences drawn from this Doctrine; that this <hi>makes us all ſlaves to the will and luſt of any vile wretch, that happens to be in the Throne, ſuch as were</hi> Tyberius, Nero, <hi>and the like,</hi> that <hi>one Arm unreſiſted may Butcher and Maſſacre an whole City or Nation, that this is enough to turn a Kingdom into a Shambles, that it is not to be thought that God would ever truſt one Man with ſuch unbounded power of doing miſchief, that to ſubmit and ſit ſtill under ſuch oppreſſion and Tyranny, as may ariſe from the abuſe of unbridled power, is to throw away our Lives, as Men weary of them, and that it is Mahumetan Doctrine, not Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But after all this it is no leſs than Demonſtration, that the caſe of the ſubject is far eaſier and ſafer, whilſt they are denied the Liberty of reſiſting, than it would have been had the ſame been indulged to them, the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences on both ſides being truly ſtated and weighed: as hath been evidently made out by ſeveral late Writers on behalf of the Government beyond all fair contradiction; and for the proof of it all appeal to the late Rebellion, called a Defenſive War, and juſtified by this Doctrine of the Lawfulneſs of reſiſting for the Preſervation of our Rights and Liberties and Religion, yet <hi>there was more Chriſtian Blood-ſhed, more Lives loſt in that quarrel, more Eſtates plundred and Confiſcated, more Families ruin'd and undone, than by all the Perſecutions and Tyrannies of all the Kings and Queens of England ſince the Conqueſt.</hi> So that it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101390:12"/>is for the good and intereſt of every ſubject, that would live quietly and peaceably and ſafely, that the Soveraign power ſhould be inveſted with an abſolute unaccounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, irreſiſtible Authority, Subordinate to none but God himſelf.</p>
            <p>And though honeſt Men may be in ſome danger from ſuch power, when it happens to be in ill hands, yet they would be continually in far greater danger, if it might be reſiſted.</p>
            <p>Was it thus Lawful on any account to take Arms, there would never be wanting a pretence for it; and ſo the Government, like a Football, would be continually toſſed from one to another, till the ſtrongeſt ran away with it, and he ſhould prevail no longer, than till ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtronger than he came and trip'd up his heels, and what ſecurity can there be for the Lives, Eſtates, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the ſubjects in the midſt of ſuch continual diſorders and revolutions? This therefore is no hard Law of our Saviours, that we ſhould not take up Arms in our own defence againſt the Magiſtrate, but very beneficial and profitable to Mankind, ſince the miſchief of ſuch reſiſtance is manifeſtly greater and more fatal, than all the ſuppoſed inconveniences that can ariſe from the abuſe of power. Some few Men may fall a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the fury or malice of a wicked Tyrant, but Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands and Ten Thouſands periſh, when Men attempt to ſave their Lives by Rebellion.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour and his Apoſtles could not but conſider this, when they ſo earneſtly forbad all reſiſtance to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101390:12"/>that ſuch unaccountable power may ſoon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate into Tyranny. They could not forget what grievous Tyrants then Reign'd in the World, moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous for their Cruelty, Injuſtice and Oppreſſion; and yet theſe muſt not be reſiſted by Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Nay if we conſider the reaſon of the caſe, it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as neceſſary, that we ſhould be forbidden to reſiſt thoſe who Rule Arbitrarily and unjuſtly, as well as the beſt and moſt gracious Princes. Since it is ſo eaſy a matter to cheat the common people into a bad opinion of their Governours, who are always apt to ſuſpect the worſt of thoſe above them. And if it had been Lawful to have reſiſted Arbitrary Power, every King good or bad would have been at the mercy of the people. For what Prince can ever hope by the moſt equal Government, and moſt mild adminiſtration to avoid the infamy of Tyranny and Arbitrary power, when our preſent moſt Gracious Soveraign, and his Father of ever bleſſed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory could not do it. This is the firſt reaſon why our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour on this occaſion forbad St. <hi>Peter</hi> the uſe of the Sword, not only becauſe the time was now come where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> was to ſuffer and dy, but becauſe St. <hi>Peter</hi> had no Authority for the drawing of it, and it was againſt the Lawful powers. <hi>All they that take the Sword, ſhall periſh with the Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. There was another reaſon for which our Saviour condemned St. <hi>Peters</hi> uſing his Sword upon this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe fighting in defence of himſelf and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was utterly inconſiſtent with his deſign, and the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101390:13"/>Nature of his Kingdom. Thus himſelf tells <hi>Pilate St. John</hi> 18.36. <hi>My Kingdom is not of this World. If my Kingdom were of this World, then would my Servants fight that I ſhould not be delivered to the Jews, but now is my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom not from hence.</hi> The Apoſtles were much miſtaken, when they thought to ſhew their zeal for their Maſter by ſetting upon and deſtroying of his enemies. They had another warfare to be engaged in. They were to glorify our Saviour by ſuffering all manner of evils chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and conrageouſly for his ſake, and this our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our taught them by this rebuke of St. <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He himſelf came into the World a pattern of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and lowlineſs, of the greateſt humility and moſt unwearied patience, and theſe were the Vertues that were to crown his Diſciples, and to recommend his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to Mankind. He did not intend to ſend out his Apoſtles as ſo many <hi>Captains</hi> and <hi>Generals</hi> by force to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the World to his obedience, but he ſent them out as Sheep amongſt Wolves, expoſed to all manner of evil treatment, which they were bravely and generouſly to endure for the ſake of their Maſter, and his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was to thrive, and flouriſh by being Perſecuted, to get ground by being oppoſed, and to be propagated by the paſſive valour and courage of Chriſtians. Force of Arms and the Sword were no likely means to beget in Men that Dovelike, Childlike, innocent and quiet, meek and gentle Spirit, which his Doctrine was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to implant in all that were called after his Name.</p>
            <p>Thus the poſture of St. <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſing the name
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101390:13"/>of Chriſt, with his Arms and Legs ſtretched out upon the Croſs at <hi>Rome,</hi> was much more becoming an Apoſtle of the Crucificed <hi>Jeſus,</hi> than brandiſhing his Sword in his hand, and fighting in defence of his Maſter. And this way did the Primitive Chriſtians and Martyrs ſhew their Love and conſtancy to their Saviour, and his Religion, by ſuffering gladly the ſpoiling of their Goods, by rejoycing in the midſt of ſcorching flames, not by fighting for it, or making it a pretence to Rebel.</p>
            <p>Though they wanted not force nor numbers ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to have oppoſed their Heathen Emperours, and ſhaken their Thrones, yet they willingly ſubmitted to the unjuſt Sentence of their Governours after the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of their Lord and Saviour; and the <hi>Apologiſt</hi> for them boaſts, that none of them ever were found Guilty of Conſpiracies againſt the Emperours, their holy Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline teaching them rather to be killed, than to kill. Thus <hi>Mauritius</hi> who Commanded the famous <hi>Thebaean Legion,</hi> which being all Chriſtians yielded themſelves to Death under <hi>Maximianus</hi> told his fellow Souldiers, how much afraid he was leſt they being Armed ſhould under pretence of defending their fellows have reſiſted the Emperour, and hindered their Martyrdom: <hi>When,</hi> as he tells them, <hi>this was forbidden by Chriſt, who would have that Sword, which the Apoſtle had drawn in his defence, to be put up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then, my Brethren, is the only caſe wherein Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion needs your valour, or calls for your courage: Not to be aſhamed of it in a wicked Generation, not to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101390:14"/>forſake it becauſe of the Croſs, with which it may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times be attended; to value pleaſing God and your own Conſciences above your Lives, or all this World calls dear. This is like true Souldiers of Jeſus Chriſt, this is to be like the great Captain of our Salvation, and to follow him as our Leader, and by this we ſhall gain admittance into his Heavenly Kingdom. But to fight for the ſetting up of Chriſts Kingdom, to Rebell that we may avoid ſuffering for our Religion, or to take up Arms for the preſervation of it was never heard of till the days of our New Reformers.</p>
            <p>In truth, all this noiſe about reſiſting for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Religion is a meer cheat and nonſenſe No earthly power can reach it, or hinder Men from being as Religious as they will, or as God hath Commanded them. It is only to ſave themſelves from ſuffering for their Religion, if the Supreme Magiſtrate ſhould at any time Perſecute the profeſſors of it, that raiſes all their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate zeal and heat, and how agreeable that is with our Saviours Command of taking up his Croſs, I leave to every Man to judge. If St. <hi>Peter</hi> might not draw his Sword to keep our Saviour from ſuffering, much leſs may we to keep our ſelves from it.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only here add one obſervation, which I find made from this fact of St. <hi>Peters;</hi> that is, He who was ſo forward to draw his Sword in defence of his Maſter, was the firſt that ſhamefully denied him, and Swore and Curs'd that he never knew him. The reaſon of which is gueſſed to be, that he was afraid of being found
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101390:14"/>out to have been the Perſon that ſmote the High Prieſts Servant, and therefore would not own any Relation to our Saviour; but however this be, I find this very uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful obſervation made upon it by an excellent Writer of our Church, that thus it very often happens, this is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the fate of ſuch Men, who are ſo ready to draw their Swords upon all occaſions for Chriſt, and his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Goſpel, againſt their Superiours, that they renounce their Saviour, and all his Beligion, before ever they lay down their Swords again. Witneſs thoſe Traitors that embrued their wicked hands in his late Majeſties Blood. What zeal for Religion did they firſt pretend? what tenderneſs of Conſcience, what honeſty and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity did they make ſhew of? and when they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd and dipt in Rebellion, what Barbarity, what Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany did they ſtick at? what Law of our Religion did they not violate? what Commandment of our Saviour did they not ſcandalouſly break? Mind it when you will, they who are ſo ready to fight for their Religion, are moſt afraid to ſuffer for it.</p>
            <p>I only beg your Patience, whilſt I draw two Inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from what I have now ſaid.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is generally enquired here, that if St. <hi>Peter</hi> upon ſo great an occaſion as this might not draw his Sword againſt the Publick Officers, by what Authority then doth the <hi>Biſhop of Rome</hi> as his Succeſſor challenge to himſelf a Superiority over Soveraign Kings and Princes, and a power to Authorize their Subjects to take up Arms againſt the, and to depoſe them: I ſay, with what
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101390:15"/>colour of reaſon can they claim this Right by vertue of their Succeſſion from St. <hi>Peter,</hi> when you ſee St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf had not leave to oppoſe or reſiſt the meaneſt Servants or Souldiers that came Armed with Publick Authority? yet we are told that no leſs a Man than <hi>Pope Boniface the Eighth</hi> undertakes to prove from this very place, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> and the Church had the power of the temporal Sword. <hi>He ſaid unto him, put up thy Sword into the ſheath</hi> uſing theſe words <hi>thy Sword.</hi> Which I only mention to ſhew you to what pitiful ſhifts Men are put, how they are forced to wrack and torture the Goſpels, when out of them they would get ſomething that ſhould countenance Sedition or Rebellion. So contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is the Doctrine of Reſiſtance to the plain Rules of our Religion, that thoſe amongſt us who have defended it in Print, have at laſt acknowledged it a <hi>Myſtery hid from former Ages, and reſerved for theſe laſt days of greater Light.</hi> They were fain to pretend a new Revelation for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From our Saviours words it undeniably appears, that all taking up Arms againſt our Soveraign Lord the King, or thoſe Commiſſionated by him, let the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence be what it will, is a plain damnable Sin. No ſubject be he of what rank or order ſoever, may draw the Sword, let the occaſion be never ſo great, without ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Authority, which he can have only from the Supreme Power it ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:101390:15"/>
            <p> I do not ſay we are bound actually to obey the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority in all things. We have an higher Lord and Maſter in Heaven, to whom the greateſt Monarch is equally accountable for all his Actions, as his meaneſt Vaſſal. And I muſt not for the ſake of any inferiour Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, renounce my Faith and Allegiance to that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly King of Kings and Lord of Lords. The only difficulty then is, if I muſt neither obey my Superiours, when they Command things unlawful, nor yet by force defend my ſelf, when they go about to puniſh me for my diſobedience, what remedy have I left me? Muſt we all loſe our Rights, Liberties, Religion and Lives, whenever they chance to be invaded by our Governours, and ſit ſtill with our hands folded up within our Boſoms?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that againſt ſuch inconveniencies as theſe, which have ſometimes happened in the World, it is confeſſed that we have no other ſecurity, but the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, which is over all his works, and the goodneſs of our Governours, who are under all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble moral obligations to rule with Juſtice, mercy and equity, and if they fail in their duties they ſhall find God a ſevere avenger. But however we are not to uſe any force towards them, any more than Children may againſt a froward and unkind Parent. Fly from them we may, and get out of their clutches, but we muſt not do the leaſt evil to them, nor ever draw our Swords againſt them. And <hi>it is the pleaſure of God when ſuch a neceſſity lies upon us, that then we ſhould exerciſe our Chriſtian Patience, and commit our Souls unto our Creatour, being
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101390:16"/>willing to lay down our Lives for his Honour from whom we received them:</hi> As the Learned <hi>Grotius</hi> Comments upon the words of my Text. This is the middle way the Goſpel preſcribes to us in ſuch difficult circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, when we cannot without Sin obey, and may not reſiſt, then quietly to ſubmit our ſelves to ſuffer Gods will.</p>
            <p>But thanks be to God, as to our ſelves in this Nation, theſe are only hard caſes ſuppoſed by thoſe, who wiſhed well at leaſt to the late horrid Conſpiracy, on purpoſe to fright people out of their Allegiance and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. For we are ſo far from having any ſuch occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or pretence for reſiſting, or uſing the Sword amongſt us, that beſides the plain unlawfulneſs and wickedneſs of ſo doing, we have all the obligations, and endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and intereſt to engage us to live quietly and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably that Subjects can poſſibly deſire.</p>
            <p>Can we wiſh for, can we conceive a more Gracious Prince than him, whom God hath ſet over us, and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto preſerved for the publick good and benefit of this Nation? How mild and gentle! how merciful and ready to forgive! So tender of his peoples welfare, ſo careful of their Liberties and Properties, that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears they are far better and more ſafe in his hands than our own. Have we not excellent Laws to ſecure to us our Civil Rights, and is not our Religion as well eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, as humane policy can do it?</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:101390:16"/>
            <p> Are we not on many accounts the happieſt and moſt fortunate people in the World, if we were but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented and pleaſed with our ſelves.</p>
            <p>That a Nation of ſo great valour and natural cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, of ſo great skill in feats of Arms, and of ſuch undaunted Spirits, which if united would be able to grap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with the ſtrongeſt and moſt potent Kingdoms in the Earth, that hath all things in it ſelf that can be called good, pleaſant or deſirable, ſhould yet weaken and deſtroy our ſelves by quarrelling amongſt our ſelves or againſt our own King, this is matter of wonder and aſtoniſhment to all the World beſide.</p>
            <p>The diſloyalty of this Nation hath much broken our reputation, and we once thought we had almoſt recover'd our credit again by the Triumphant Reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his preſent Majeſty, (whom God long preſerve) till theſe late diviſions, and commotions, and freſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, and renewed attempts againſt the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, have ſunk us low in the eſteem of all our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Nations.</p>
            <p>But Bleſſed be God, that this Poyſon of Faction and Sedition hath not infected all ſorts of Men. There was preſerved a remnant that never bowed their knees to <hi>Baal,</hi> nor were carried away by the popular ſtream; who preſerved their integrity and Loyalty intire in the midſt of that crooked and perverſe Generation. This Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly here preſent is ſufficient inſtance of the truth of what I ſay.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:101390:17"/>
            <p> May the King never want ſuch Subjects of ſuch skill and courage, of ſuch Loyalty and honeſty to defend his Royal Perſon and happy Government againſt Foreign Invaſions, and inteſtine Factions and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions. And give me leave to end all with this Prayer, and I know you are ſuch lovers of Peace, that you will all ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to it, However neceſſary the terrour of your Arms may be to the defence of the King and Church, yet God grant that neither of them may ever have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to make uſe of your Sword, or try either your skill or courage.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Three Books lately Publiſhed by <hi>Samuel Parker,</hi> D. D. Archdeacon of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. AN Account of the Government of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church for the Firſt 600 years.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Religion and Loyalty, the <hi>Firſt part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Religion and Loyalty, the <hi>Second part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo the right Foundation of Quietneſs, Obedience and Concord, by <hi>Clement Ellis,</hi> newly publiſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All ſold by</hi> John Baker <hi>at the</hi> Three Pigeons in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101390:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
